Finding Aid for Irene Tejada papers, 1928-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Irene Tejada papers 1928-1998, 1950-1970
Tejada, Irene.
2 linear feet
04104 Aa 2
Assistant professor of art and of education at the University of Michigan, K-12 art teacher at University School (1955-1970), and professional artist. Emphasis on visual, teaching, and historical materials from University School, including slides and photographs of students in educational facilities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came to the library in April of 2002 (donor no. 9334.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Irene Tejada was best known for her love of art and her friendly personality. In her many years of teaching, beginning in 1942, she shared her passion for art with hundreds of students in Michigan schools and abroad.
Her love of learning equaled her love for teaching as she not only earned a master's degree in design but also took numerous courses beyond her graduate work. Tejada became known as an expert on the use of indigenous materials for the production of arts and crafts, and had a particular interest in multicultural art. Her master's thesis was entitled "Persian Turquoise Glazes."
Tejada's early teaching career led her to schools in the Virgin Islands, Puerto Rico, and Detroit, and she also taught at West Virginia State College before coming to the University of Michigan in 1950. During the years 1950 to 1955 she completed her master's degree and served as Staff Artist for the UM Audio-Visual Education Center, working as an illustrator of various materials and designer of educational exhibitions. In 1955 she joined the staff at the UM laboratory school, known as University School, as an art teacher where she taught K-12 students until 1970, when the school closed. In her later career she became an assistant professor in both the School of Education and the School of Art at the University of Michigan and was granted emeritus status in 1989.
Many students came back to visit Tejada over the years and acknowledged her teaching as the origin for their later involvement in the arts. She believed that children's art education should aim for the same quality as advanced art courses and enthusiastically exhibited student artwork in the schools and in the community. She was awarded Teacher of the Year at University School in 1968, and in 1991, received recognition for her lifelong dedication to art education from the Michigan Art Education Association.
Tejada's professional work included publication in the School Arts magazine and Brown Bag Ideas from Many Cultures, a resource she created for use in multicultural arts units. She was also a member of various organizations and committees including the National and Michigan Art Education Associations, the School Arts Coordinating Committee, Delta Kappa Gamma (a teachers' sorority supporting women in education), the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA), and a committee, founded by Tejada in 1972, for incorporation of a multicultural curriculum in Ann Arbor Public Schools. The committee's multicultural courses were in place at the University of Michigan by 1973 and the inclusion of such programs was mandated in the State Legislature in 1974.
As an artist, teacher, friend, and innovator Irene Tejada was respected by her colleagues and students alike. She died on October 25, 1999, and her obituary can be found in the University of Michigan Publication The University Record from December 13, 1999.
The Irene Tejada Papers include materials from the professional career of Irene Tejada, as well as materials documenting the history of University School. Organized into three series, Teaching/Professional Materials, Visual Materials, and University School Related Materials, the papers span the years 1928-1998 with the bulk of the materials from 1950 to 1970. The strength of the collection lies in the many depictions of life and activities at the University School through both visual and non-visual materials.
Subjects:
Tejada, Irene.; Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Art--Study and teaching (Elementary)--Michigan.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; University Elementary School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan. University School.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Teaching/Professional Materials 1953-1985
  The Teaching/Professional Materials series includes two subseries. The first, General Materials, contains a variety of materials from Tejada's career including published artwork, class and teaching materials, correspondence, etc. The second subseries, Exhibits and Displays, focuses on displays which Tejada designed, but also includes non-visual display materials such as exhibit announcements and programs. The largest group of materials comes from Tejada's work on "UM Presidents and the School of Education 1817-1980" which was a display in University School as well as a separate book. Researchers should also consult the "Slides" and "Photographs" areas within the Visual Materials series to see displays by University School art students.
  - General Materials
    - Art by Tejada 1953-1972 (Box 1)
      (Publication covers, brochures, etc.)
    - Audio-visual research for use in Education 1954-1971 (Box 1)
    - Class materials and Schedules, undated 1957-1968 (Box 1)
    - Junior High Teaching materials 1959-1965 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1955-1965 (Box 1)
    - Proposed Art Club Constitution undated (Box 1)
    - Staff Bulletins 1955, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Tejada's Resumé, [1985 (Box 1)
    - University School Special Events 1961-1968 (Box 1)
      (Programs and assemblies)
    - Yearbook (Nunc Dimittis) Awards, artwork, and instruction manual, 1937-1967 (Box 1)
    - Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) 1954-1957 (Box 1)
      (Brochures, meeting minutes, etc.)
  - Exhibits and Displays
    - General Displays undated, 1953 (Box 1)
      (photographs and negatives from various displays by Tejada)
    - UM Presidents and the School of Education 1817-1980, 1980
      (Designed by Tejada, includes exhibit text, photographs, notes, and 1 bound book)
      - Display Text (Box 1)
      - Display Folder #1 "The University in Detroit 1817" (Box 1)
      - Display Folder #2 "Ann Arbor Beginnings 1837-1871" (Box 1)
      - Display Folder #3 "The Angell Years 1871-1909" (Box 1)
      - Display Folder #4 "The Expanding University 1909-1951" (Box 1)
      - Display Folder #5 "A Model School" (Box 1)
      - Display Folder #6 "At Mid-Century 1951-1967" (Box 1)
      - Display Folder #7 "Shaping the Future" (Box 1)
      - Display Materials and unused photographs (Box 1)
      - Book Materials (Box 1)
        (includes photographs and negatives)
      - Final Book (Box 1)
    - Non-visual Display Materials undated, 1956-1963 (Box 1)
      (Exhibit and display programs, announcements, newspaper articles, and sketch of main University School display case, see also "Photographs" and "Slides" in the "Visual Materials" series)
- Visual Materials 1929-1981, undated
  The next series, Visual Materials, focuses primarily on photographs and slides showing University School students, student art projects, and displays. Also included are photographs of scenes from the University School facilities, University School faculty, and metallic printing plates mounted on woodblocks.
  - Photo Albums, 1958-1961, 1968-1970 (Box 2)
    (Grades N-6)
  - Photographs
    (mostly undated, see also "Exhibits and Displays" in the "Teaching/Professional Materials" series)
    - Art Students undated, 1943 (Box 2)
      (includes contact prints)
    - Students with Puppets undated, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - UM Campus and Unidentified undated (Box 2)
    - University School Displays 1939, 1955, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Student Portraits 1961 (Box 2)
      (2 rolls, Grades N-6 and Grade 12)
    - University School Student Portraits and Activities, undated 1929, 1950, 1963, 1968 (Box 2)
    - University School Scenes and Faculty, undated 1964 (Box 2)
      (includes negatives)
  - Slides 1955-1981
    (see also "Exhibits and Displays" in the "Teaching/Professional Materials" series)
    - Art Students and Projects undated, 1960, 1962-1963, 1970 (Box 2)
      (Elementary through High School)
    - Art Students with Puppets, undated 1955, 1957-1959, 1962, 1965, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Montage (High School gym) 1962 and Rackham Exhibit, undated, 1964 (Box 2)
    - University School Christmas Displays 1955-1967, 1979, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
      (3 pages of slides)
  - Woodblocks undated (Box 2)
    (various prints of people and activities, may have been used for yearbook art)
- University School Related Materials 1928-1998
  The last series, University School Related Materials, includes materials which focus on University School as a whole rather than on Tejada's personal work. Examples include school publications, directories, alumni activities, and documents regarding the closing of University School. Some materials in the Publications and the Historical and General Materials folders originate from before Tejada joined the University School staff in 1955. Researchers should observe that notes in this series indicate a few instances where Tejada is specifically mentioned or involved.
  - Alumni Newsletters and Reunions 1981, 1988, 1998 (Box 2)
    (Tejada is mentioned in the 1988 reunion packet)
  - Directories 1959, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
  - Historical and General Materials 1928-1967 (Box 2)
    (Student handbook, school song, school history and standards, etc. Also includes materials on Ione Baker, a teacher at University School who may have been a relative of Tejada)
  - Parent Newsletters 1958, 1963, 1964 (Box 2)
    (Tejada mentioned in April and November-December 1958 issues, and in May 1964 issue)
  - Publications 1928-1968
    - The Broadcaster 1928-1968 (Box 2)
      (Tejada mentioned in September 23, 1955 issue)
    - Nuggets of News 1965 (Box 2)
      (Tejada mentioned in December 16, 1965 issue)
    - Teaching Core "Tamarack Tales," 1965 (Box 2)
    - University High School Descriptive Booklet 1929 (Box 2)
  - School Closing 1962-1969
    - Parent-Teacher Association (PTA) reactions 1963-1967 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Regents and School of Education Documents 1962-1969 (Box 2)
      (includes meeting minutes, reports, newspaper article, etc.)